<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<feed version="0.3" xmlns="http://purl.org/atom/ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Life on the Rivers Edge</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/" />
  <modified>2005-08-07T20:27:20Z</modified>
  <tagline>Fact and Fiction from America&apos;s most beautiful rivertown.</tagline>
  <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1</id>
  <generator url="http://www.movabletype.org/" version="2.661">Movable Type</generator>
  <copyright>Copyright (c) 2005, egyarnetsky</copyright>
  <entry>
    <title>Last MovableType entry</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000601.html" />
    <modified>2005-08-07T20:27:20Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-08-07T16:27:20-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.601</id>
    <created>2005-08-07T20:27:20Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">I *finally* finished my second summer session and I&apos;m only waiting to get my grade from my final paper. I think my paper on &quot;blogging for accessibility&quot; turned out pretty decent. I may post it later to get some feedback...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Life</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>I *finally* finished my second summer session and I'm only waiting to get my grade from my final paper. I think my paper on "blogging for accessibility" turned out pretty decent. I may post it later to get some feedback on it.</p>

<p>The treat I'm giving myself for surviving the summer is to move to a new blogging system. I got tired of my MovableType 2.66. I thought about upgrading to MT 3.1, but then I'd have to pay to do my wife's website on it.</p>

<p>So I am currently working on a move to <a href="http://www.textpattern.com">Textpattern</a> and should make the site live within a couple days. While it takes some getting used to, I'm enjoying the flexibility it's provides. For example, having a sidebar blog is now very easy so I now have a place for short posts like mini-reviews and fun websites.</p>

<p>The program is still under development, they are on a final candidate release and just locked down the features about a week ago. As a result, there are very few templates to work from so I cobbled a few of them together to get what I want. I figure I can be more creative on a future release. </p>

<p>To get a feel for what people are doing with Textpattern, try a visit over to <a href="http://txpmagazine.kbbu.de/">TXP Magazine</a> and take a look at the <a href="http://txpmagazine.kbbu.de/all_sites/">sites collection</a>.</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>May you live in interesting times</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000600.html" />
    <modified>2005-07-31T01:39:39Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-30T21:39:39-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.600</id>
    <created>2005-07-31T01:39:39Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Right now I feel like I was given one of those fortune cookies that read—“May you live in interesting times” or some such. Right now I’m in over my head with homework. In five weeks I’ve written more than 50...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Life</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Right now I feel like I was given one of those fortune cookies that read—“May you live in interesting times” or some such.</p>

<p>Right now I’m in over my head with homework. In five weeks I’ve written more than 50 pages in papers and I have at least another dozen to go before I can quit next week. I think the last time I wrote that much in a short period of time was for our local paper during the 1997 flood.</p>

<p>Either way, after this class I’ll be a third of the way toward a masters degree.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, I have once again shuffled myself into the middle of a historic preservation hullabaloo as a member of the Madison Historic District Board of Review.</p>

<p>A property owner pre-meditatively violated our historic district ordinance after we turned him down for vinyl windows on his 19th century industrial/commercial building. All of the sudden, my name’s been in the paper about every other day and on local online forums.</p>

<p>The board is in a bad position. One one hand we have a very weak ordinance with no design guidelines. On the other our community has a strong libertarian streak where people don’t like to be told what to do with their properties. It amazes me that through all this some people seem to think we enjoy doing what we do.</p>

<p>I’m learning to live with the notion I’ll be a punching bag for people’s views on preservation in Madison. However, I just hope people will continue allowing me to serve them in peace at the library (if that makes sense).</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>36 years ago today...the moon</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000599.html" />
    <modified>2005-07-20T17:35:04Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-20T13:35:04-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.599</id>
    <created>2005-07-20T17:35:04Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">I think it&apos;s appropriate that we almost have a full moon today as today&apos;s the anniversary of the first moon landing. If you want to get a feel of what it looked like peering down at the moon from Eagle...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>News</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>I think it's appropriate that we almost have a full moon today as today's the anniversary of the first moon landing.</p>

<p>If you want to get a feel of what it looked like peering down at the moon from Eagle as it fell toward the surface, check out <a title="Google Moon - Lunar Landing Sites" href="http://moon.google.com/">Google Moon</a>.</p>

<p>[<b>Easter egg alert</b>: Don't forget to zoom in!]</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Oh Scotty, you were the intelligent life down here</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000598.html" />
    <modified>2005-07-20T17:29:55Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-20T13:29:55-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.598</id>
    <created>2005-07-20T17:29:55Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">James Doohan, the gentleman who brought Montgomery Scott alive on Star Trek died this morning. Scotty and Leonard &quot;Bones&quot; McCoy were my favorites. I love that he never got sick of the &quot;phrase&quot;: In a 1998 interview, Doohan was asked...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>News</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>James Doohan, the gentleman who brought Montgomery Scott alive on Star Trek died this morning. Scotty and Leonard "Bones" McCoy were my favorites. </p>

<p>I love that he never got sick of the "phrase": </p>

<blockquote>In a 1998 interview, Doohan was asked if he ever got tired of hearing the line ''Beam me up, Scotty.''

<p>''I'm not tired of it at all,'' he replied. ''Good gracious, it's been said to me for just about 31 years. It's been said to me at 70 miles an hour across four lanes on the freeway. I hear it from just about everybody. It's been fun.''</blockquote></p>

<p>Here's his obit: <a title="'Star Trek' Star James Doohan Dies - New York Times" href="http://www.nytimes.com/aponline/arts/AP-Obit-Doohan.html">'Star Trek' Star James Doohan Dies - New York Times</a></p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Trying to shift the news cycle</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000597.html" />
    <modified>2005-07-20T03:20:38Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-19T23:20:38-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.597</id>
    <created>2005-07-20T03:20:38Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">The news for the past few weeks was that Bush planned to take some time and ponder his choice for Supreme Court ... then suddenly poof! Out comes a nomination out of the hat. (Bush Chooses Judge Roberts for Supreme...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Politics</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>The news for the past few weeks was that Bush planned to take some time and ponder his choice for Supreme Court ... then suddenly poof! Out comes a nomination out of the hat. (<a title="Bush Chooses Judge Roberts for Supreme Court - New York Times" href="http://www.nytimes.com/reuters/politics/politics-bush-court.html">Bush Chooses Judge Roberts for Supreme Court - New York Times</a>)</p>

<p>Can you say "Bush is desperate to change the news away from Rove?"<br />
</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Costco: Retail done right?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000596.html" />
    <modified>2005-07-20T02:42:38Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-19T22:42:38-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.596</id>
    <created>2005-07-20T02:42:38Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Would you shop at a warehouse store that paid its employees well yet still had good price? Would you shop at a warehouse store that doesn&apos;t roll over at every whim of Wall Street? Costco is a very, very interesting...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>News</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Would you shop at a warehouse store that paid its employees well yet still had good price?</p>

<p>Would you shop at a warehouse store that doesn't roll over at every whim of Wall Street?  </p>

<p><a href="http://www.costco.com">Costco</a> is a very, very interesting business. I've never been to one, but I am definitely planning to look for one.</p>

<p>Check out this article in the New York Times (free registration) to get a feel for the place. <a title="How Costco Became the Anti-Wal-Mart - New York Times" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/17/business/yourmoney/17costco.html?incamp=article_popular_2&pagewanted=all">How Costco Became the Anti-Wal-Mart.</a></p>

<p>The kicker for me? They support Democrats! Here's their profile on <a href="http://www.buyblue.org/detail.php?corpId=17">BuyBlue.com</b>. </p>

<p><b>Bottom line</b>: Progressive businesses can be profitable and they don't have to make their bucks on the backs of your employees or customers.</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bush &quot;shifting&quot; on Plame blame? Try &quot;shafting&quot;...</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000595.html" />
    <modified>2005-07-19T01:55:49Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-18T21:55:49-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.595</id>
    <created>2005-07-19T01:55:49Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">OK now, on June 10, 2004, President Bush was asked if he would fire anyone who had anything to do with the leaking Valerie Plame-Wilson&apos;s name as a covert CIA agent. Bush responded &quot;yes&quot; and his spokeman since repeated the...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Politics</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>OK now, on June 10, 2004, President Bush was asked if he would fire anyone who had anything to do with the leaking Valerie Plame-Wilson's name as a covert CIA agent. Bush responded "yes" and his spokeman since repeated the statement to the White House press corps.</p>

<p>How come today, he is suddenly "shifting" his position as USA Today put it?<br />
Now  he'll <a href="http://www.usatoday.com/news/washington/2005-07-18-bush-rove_x.htm">"if someone committed a <b><i>crime</i></b>, they will no longer work in my administration."</a></p>

<p>To me that essentially says he <b><i>knows</i></b> someone (or someones) in his administration most definitely messed with Plame, but he doesn't want to do a damn thing about it.</p>

<p>Striking out at Plame because her husband discredited the Bush rally cry to war would be playground petty if she were not with the CIA. However, she was an agent and to me that borders on treason.</p>

<p>Why? Consider this question... if Plame is outted as a covert agent, isn't that in turn going to out anyone who covertly worked with her?</p>

<p>This isn't the only thing about his statement today that drives me bats-- how about the notion that he's known about the allegation for two years and says he "doesn't know all the facts." For that to be true he must have told everyone involved to keep him in the dark so he wouldn't have to testify.</p>

<p>If there's any saving grace its that the White House press corps finally has a string to pull. They suddenly seem to realize they've been lied to and are trying to unravel the mess we're in. Mind you, the odds of that happening are still pretty slim, but you can't blame a cat for dreaming.</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince arrives</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000594.html" />
    <modified>2005-07-16T15:20:03Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-16T11:20:03-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.594</id>
    <created>2005-07-16T15:20:03Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Darlene just got an email that the new Harry Potter book had shipped. &quot;Shoot, I guess that means I won&apos;t get it today. Oh, who knows maybe they&apos;ll deliver it later. You can always hope.&quot; Well, not 10 minutes later,...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Life</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Darlene just got an email that the new Harry Potter book had shipped. "Shoot, I guess that means I won't get it today. Oh, who knows maybe they'll deliver it later. You can always hope."</p>

<p>Well, not 10 minutes later, I hear a light knock on the door. I had to scramble to get downstairs. The mailman was already down the street, but I managed to catch him.</p>

<p>Of course, he hands me a box labeled "Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince."</p>

<p>I now have a happy potter reading Harry Potter...</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Music Thursday</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000593.html" />
    <modified>2005-07-15T03:48:57Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-14T23:48:57-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.593</id>
    <created>2005-07-15T03:48:57Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">I bought some new CDs for the first time in probably years. I had been promising Darlene some new jazz for a while and now that I&apos;ve played a few tracks I think I chose well. Here&apos;s what I snagged...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Culture</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>I bought some new CDs for the first time in probably years. I had been promising Darlene some new jazz for a while and now that I've played a few tracks I think I chose well. Here's what I snagged from <a href="http://www.houseohits.com/hoh/index.htm">House O' Hits Records</a>:</p>

<ul>
<li>"<b>Stay Loose...Jimmy Smith Sings Again</b>": This guy is great on the Hammond B3 organ. One of his better albums from the 1960s.</li>
<li>"<b>The Definitive Chet Baker</b>": So far I like his trumpet better than his vocals, but not bad when he combines the two. I bought this one on a whim.</li>
<li>"<b>Compact Jazz Lionel Hampton</b>": This is not one of the better Hampton collections, but I love him on the vibraphone. Hey it was a used CD.</li>
</ul>
The test obviously is whether she'll like them...]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Poor Scottie</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000592.html" />
    <modified>2005-07-12T03:25:45Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-11T23:25:45-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.592</id>
    <created>2005-07-12T03:25:45Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Holy cow! Who woke up the White House Press Corps? The press briefing with Scott McClellan was full of attack dogs....</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>News</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Holy cow! Who woke up the White House Press Corps? The <a title="Press Briefing by Scott McClellan" href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/news/releases/2005/07/20050711-3.html">press briefing with Scott McClellan</a> was full of attack dogs.</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How does blogging impact web accessibility?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000591.html" />
    <modified>2005-07-09T02:14:03Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-08T22:14:03-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.591</id>
    <created>2005-07-09T02:14:03Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Right now I&apos;m taking &quot;Resources and Technology for Patrons with Special Needs&quot; and I&apos;m doing research for a 20 page paper (20 pages maximum thank God). I write this and Darlene, reading over my shoulder, says &quot;Ha! Knowing you, you&apos;ll...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>MLS</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Right now I'm taking "Resources and Technology for Patrons with Special Needs" and I'm doing research for a 20 page paper (20 pages maximum thank God).</p>

<p>I write this and Darlene, reading over my shoulder, says "Ha! Knowing you, you'll have a hard time keeping it to 20 pages." I'm glad she's optimistic.</p>

<p>Either way, I'm opening this to the wisdom of the masses. </p>

<p>My topic is how does blogging (and content management software in general) impact accessibility of the resulting websites? Is the software itself user-friendly to bloggers (or would-be bloggers) who have sight impairments? What can we do to improve the situation?</p>

<p>While much of designing blogs for accessibility echoes accessible web design in general, there are other things that are unique to blogging software. For example, in order to post comments on some sites, you have to type in the distorted letters seen in a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captcha">captcha illustration</a>. That'd be impossible for someone using a screen reader. </p>

<p>In the case of <a href="http://www.blogger.com">blogger.com</a>, you have to type in the captcha before you can even get a blog. Understandable? Yes, as it keeps computers from signing up for millions of blogs. Accessible? No. How can a person who is blind blog when they can't get a blog from Blogger?</p>

<p>That's one example. Right now I'm harvesting articles for my research. If any of you have any ideas on avenues of exploration, etc., let me know... </p>

<p><a href="mailto:egyarnetsky@mac.com">Email me on the rivers edge</a></p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lost Civil Liberties</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000590.html" />
    <modified>2005-07-07T01:38:53Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-06T21:38:53-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.590</id>
    <created>2005-07-07T01:38:53Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">My mom visited us just before the holiday and brought us an Alice in Wonderland mug that had a disappearing Cheshire cat when you put in hot water. The mug is great (it doesn&apos;t hurt that I love the Sir...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Politics</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>My mom visited us just before the holiday and brought us an Alice in Wonderland mug that had a disappearing Cheshire cat when you put in hot water. The mug is great (it doesn't hurt that I love the Sir John Tenniel's illustrations). </p>

<p>Today I stumbled upon another product from the Unemployed Philosphers Guild: the <a title="Unemployed Philosophers Guild: Lost Civil Liberties mug" href="http://www.philosophersguild.com/index.lasso?page_mode=Product_Detail&item=0236">Lost Civil Liberties mug</a>.</p>

<p>Amazing how a cup of coffee can share such truths.</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Organic groceries in Madison!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000589.html" />
    <modified>2005-07-04T02:40:27Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-07-03T22:40:27-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.589</id>
    <created>2005-07-04T02:40:27Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Madison has joined the big leagues of food. A new grocery open here downtown that offers organic food, fruit, vegatables, meats and cheeses. The variety is wonderful. Check out Local Harvest Market. They&apos;re planning an &quot;e-market&quot; that will open soon...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Life</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Madison has joined the big leagues of food. A new grocery open here downtown that offers organic food, fruit, vegatables, meats and cheeses. The variety is wonderful.</p>

<p>Check out <a href="http://www.localharvestmarket.com">Local Harvest Market</a>. They're planning an "e-market" that will open soon so you can get an idea of what they're carrying.</p>

<p>What amazes me is they even have FRESH fish flown in from the coast three times a week. I don't know the last time I've had fresh fish. Also every kind of meat you can imagine-- we can even get bison, rabbit and duck. If you have the opportunity, you should try organic free-range chicken eggs. They really are pretty amazing.</p>

<p>They also have prepared meals. We had beef curry rice for dinner tonight. They also had grilled swordfish with pineapple and mango sauce. They'll even make you sandwiches from fresh baked bread and premium Boar's Head meats from their deli cut to order. I'm told sushi is also coming soon.</p>

<p>I know one of the people who will be working there and she said they all attended workshops to learn about the products they'll be selling. Indeed, she attended a fullday on just wines and cheeses.</p>

<p>While I doubt I could afford to buy all my food there, but I am very much looking forward to sampling the fare, this will be fun-- real food!</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>&quot;Knowledge for Sale: Why American libraries are in trouble&quot;</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000587.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-27T15:10:58Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-27T11:10:58-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.587</id>
    <created>2005-06-27T15:10:58Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">[Updated: Utne street librarian Chris Dodge today sent me the links to the articles. Also minor edits] The July/August issue of Utne magazine features an article by &quot;street librarian&quot; Chris Dodge entitled &quot;Knowledge for sale: Why American libraries are in...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Library</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>[<b>Updated</b>: Utne street librarian Chris Dodge today sent me the links to the articles. Also minor edits]</p>

<p>The July/August issue of Utne magazine features an article by "street librarian" Chris Dodge entitled "Knowledge for sale: Why American libraries are in trouble."</p>

<p>If you want to know what the left thinks about libraries, I consider this a must read article. <a href="http://www.utne.com/magazine/newsstand/utne130_knowledge-for-sale.pdf">Knowledge for Sale</a> (also <a href="http://www.utne.com/magazine/newsstand/utne130_monastic-librarians.pdf">Monastic Librarians</a>). From an academic standpoint, there's not a ton of depth, but it's very interesting nonetheless.</p>

<p>He hit on some interesting issues, some of which I struggle with myself at my library-- specifically issues on purchasing and cataloging. I agree with him on both issues. Here are his thoughts and my thoughts...</p>

<p>On purchasing... </p>

<p>If we continue to move toward the demand-model of material selection and/or outsourse the selection process, Dodge argues the collections will become skewed to the popular and mass appeal. As a result, we ignore the minority communities or minority interests. I wholeheartedly agree, though I think people have come to expect the demand model from libraries. </p>

<p>At our library I do some AV purchasing and subscribed to the Film Movement series from Recorded Books. I like it because we now have same access to award-winning films in little ol' Madison as the hot shots in New York and LA. It's a total of 12 DVDs a year, not a large number considering I order at least 180 DVDs a year. </p>

<p>While a number of people have told me they liked the series, one person wrote in our annual survey (paraphased) "stop buying all that foreign junk."  After some thought I concluded the problem wasn't one of an an imbalanced collection, but rather all the popular titles I've purchased are constantly in circulation so you have to show up at exactly the right time (or put them on hold) to snag them. As a result, the collection certainly looks skewed to the obtuse. I think I'll create a paper catalog of DVD titles as people rarely bother to search the catalog to see if we have a title.</p>

<p>On Cataloging... </p>

<p>Dodge also wrote how our standardized catalog systems are unintuitive, severely hampering access to materials.</p>

<p>Having taken "bibliographic access and control" I certainly understand the need for standardization. Obviously, a catalog without controlled vocabulary and name/subject authority is obviously chaos.</p>

<p>However, I'd definitely consider myself a Sandynista. Dodge wrote about the work of Hennepin County (minn.) cataloger Sandy Berman who, through extensive bibliographic record notes and alternative titles and subjects, created a catalog that was very user friendly. Unfortunately, in the name of standardization, the library system reversed his work after he retired. I think that's a sickening shame. </p>

<p>We have a generally easy to use online catalog (Sirsi iBistro), but it is severely lacking in that is has no capabilities to share sees/see alsos. Thus the only way to get around this is to do a Berman-style bibliographic record. (although it'd obviously be better for Sirsi and other search engines to get their act together).</p>

<p>Similarly, authors have to be types in "last name, first name" yet there are no obvious "tips" on the page to tell anyone that.  A person can go away thinking we have absolutely no books on a topic of interest.</p>

<p>Similarly, our library is now in the process of starting a second digital library. On the first I argued we needed alternative catagories as noone will type in dwellings when they are searching for photos of "Madison homes." I was overruled by a very experienced and very wise cataloger who stressed we needed to stick with standards. I am grateful to her as starting off on the right foot and doing the project "right" has helped us get a federal grant to do a second digital library. </p>

<p>This new project is one of the first in the Indiana Digital Library project that aims to create digital projects that can be shared so they can be "harvested" by search engines. Standardization is a must for this to work, yet the problem of "will a person search using LC subject terms?" still exists. </p>

<p>A number of us agreed at a workshop sponsored by the Indiana State Library that we needed to include alternative subjects in addition to official "LC" subject terms. </p>

<p>This whole debate obviously opens a whole can of worms, but I think it's one that needs to be opened. Fried worms anyone?</p>

<p>Here are two links...</p>

<p><a href="http://madison-jeffco.cdm.oclc.org">The Lemen Collection</a></p>

<p>This is the first digital library the Madison-Jefferson County Public Library did. I was in charge of the tech side of the project, scanning and customizing the web templates to fit our desires.</p>

<p><a href="http://openstacks.net/os/archives/000732.html#000732">Open Stacks #1</a></p>

<p>This is the first podcast of Open Stacks by my friend Greg Schwartz. His premiere episode delves deeply into Adam Mathes' paper on folksonomies. If you're interested in cataloging I think you'd find the podcast (an mp3 audio file) to be fascinating.</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Madison in spring album</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/archives/000588.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-23T12:24:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-23T08:24:09-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.ontheriversedge.com,2005://1.588</id>
    <created>2005-06-23T12:24:09Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">It&apos;s a couple months late, but I finally have time to post some more photos. Once again these are some photos Darlene took. She&apos;s pretty much commendeered the camera. Either way, we&apos;re dedicating this album to Nathan and Anne, a...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>egyarnetsky</name>
      <url>http://www.ontheriversedge.com</url>
      <email>egy@mudcatpottery.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Madison</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.ontheriversedge.com/">
      <![CDATA[<p>It's a couple months late, but I finally have time to post some more photos. Once again these are some photos Darlene took. She's pretty much commendeered the camera.</p>

<p>Either way, we're dedicating this album to Nathan and Anne, a truly wonderful couple from Dallas, Texas, we met yesterday. They are considering a move to the most beautiful rivertown in America and were quizzing us. Yet we found many commonalities that led to four hours of fun conversation. We hope to someday have them as neighbors.</p>

<p>--Hope y'all had a safe drive home and here are some photos to hold you over.</p>

<p><a href="http://homepage.mac.com/egyarnetsky/PhotoAlbum6.html">Madison in Spring</a>, photos by Darlene Yarnetsky</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>

</feed>